Adams Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Adams Family Papers 1776-1948 (bulk 1794-1846)
MSS10199
Adams family
230 items 2 containers .8 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Chiefly correspondence of John Quincy Adams dated 1801-1846. Also includes correspondence and miscellany relating to other family members.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Adams family.; Adams, Abigail, 1744-1818. Abigail Adams papers.; Adams, Charles Francis, 1807-1886. Charles Francis Adams papers.; Adams, Charles Francis, 1835-1915. Charles Francis Adams papers.; Adams, Henry, 1838-1918. Henry Adams papers.; Adams, Herbert Baxter, 1850-1901--Correspondence.; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848. John Quincy Adams papers.; Adams, John, 1735-1826. John Adams papers.; Adams, Louisa Catherine, 1775-1852. Louisa Catherine Adams papers.; Adams, Samuel, 1722-1803. Samuel Adams papers.; Blunt, Joseph, 1792-1860--Correspondence.; Everett, Alexander Hill, 1790-1847--Correspondence.; Jefferson, Thomas 1743-1826--Correspondence.; Madison, James, 1751-1836--Correspondence.; Welsh, Robert--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Historical Association.
Places
Massachusetts--Politics and government.; Massachusetts--Social life and customs.; United States--Politics and government--1775-1783.; United States--Politics and government--1783-1865.
Occupations
Authors.; Cabinet officers.; Diplomats.; Historians.; Presidents' spouses--United States.; Presidents--United States.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Massachusetts.; Vice-Presidents--United States.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of the Adams Family were received by the Library of Congress through gift and purchase, 1901-2000.
Additional Guides
An index to the correspondence of John Quincy Adams is available in the Manuscript Reading Room.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the Adams family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The Adams Family Papers span the years 1776 to 1948 with the bulk dated 1794-1846. Chiefly comprising correspondence of John Quincy Adams, the collection also includes correspondence and other material relating to Abigail Adams, Charles Francis Adams (1807-1886), Charles Francis Adams (1835-1915), Henry Adams, John Adams, Louisa Catherine Adams, and Samuel Adams. Henry Adams included his address to the American Historical Association in a letter dated 1894 to Herbert Baxter Adams. Many of the items are transcripts, photocopies, and other reproductions. Some of the twentieth century items are explanatory cover letters or printed material. Other correspondents include Joseph Blunt, Alexander Hill Everett, Thomas Jefferson, James Madison, and Robert Welsh, Jr.
The papers are arranged alphabetically by name of family member.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm74010199
Container List
- Adams, Abigail (1744-1818) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1790, 1796, 1800, 1813-1815 (Box 1)
  - Lock of hair, undated (Box 1)
- Adams, Charles Francis (1807-1886) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1851-1853, 1862, 1873 (Box 1)
    - Seward, William H., to Adams, draft with notes, 1861 (Box 1)
- Adams, Charles Francis (1835-1915), correspondence, 1899-1911, (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Adams, Henry (1838-1918), correspondence, 1863, 1894, 1914 (Box 1)
- Adams, John (1735-1826) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1776-1817, 1826, 1948, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Miscellany (Box 1)
    - Commission to Seth Lewis, 1800 (Box 1)
    - Facsimiles of Adams's signature, newspaper clipping, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Will and tombstone inscription, undated (Box 1)
- Adams, John Quincy (1767-1848) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1801-1830, (6 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1831-1838, 1846, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Miscellany (Box 2)
    - Account of the debate on the annexation of Texas in the U.S. House of Representatives, fragment, 1838 (Box 2)
    - Deed to Richard Morsell and receipts for payment for land in Washington, D.C., 1840-1847 (Box 2)
    - Land grants (Box 2)
      - Ormsby, Robert, 1826 (Box 2)
      - Rood, William, 1826 (Box 2)
    - Letter announcing release of Adams from post as resident minister to the Batavian Republic, signed by Timothy Pickering, 1797 (Box 2)
    - “Livre d’or de la Bibliotheque de la Ville de Graned,” copy of page containing Adams’s signature, 1814 (Box 2)
    - Print from engraved portrait, with signature, undated (Box 2)
    - Remarks to Congress at the death of William Soden Hastings, holograph, 1842, with note by Mary Earle, 1864 (Box 2)
    - Seal impression made by great-granddaughter, Abigail Adams, 1896 (Box 2)
    - Sketches of Adams and other negotiators of the Treaty of Ghent, 1815 (Box 2)
- Adams, Louisa Catherine (1775-1852) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1832-1836, 1848 (Box 2)
  - Miscellany (Box 2)
    - “The Indestructible Church,” leaflet concerning church where Louisa and John Quincy Adams were married, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Poems, 1827, undated (Box 2)
- Adams, Samuel (1722-1803), correspondence, 1775-1789 (Box 2)